Guide to the Helen Burr Smith Papers 1918-1980 MS 0573
New-York Historical Society
Helen Burr Smith papers
1918-1980
New-York Historical Society
Smith, Helen Burr
MS 0573
27 Linear feet in 76 boxes
This collection consists of the research notes, correspondence, and personal papers of Helen Burr Smith (1892-1980), an authority on Colonial American silversmiths and portrait painters.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 6 series by subject:
Series I: Research
Series II: General Correspondence
Series III: Catalogs
Series IV: Documents Related to Colonial Silver
Series V: Personal Papers
Serries VI: Published Volumes
Biographical / Historical
Helen Burr Smith (1892-1980) was an authority on early American silver and portrait painters. She was a direct descendant of Michael Hillegas, the first Treasurer of the United States, and a collateral descendant of Aaron Burr, and her family history and genealogy was also a focus of her research. Smith was a frequent contributor to the New-York Historical Society Quarterly, the New York Genealogical and Biographical Society Record, American Collector, Antiques Magazine, and the New York Sun newspaper.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Helen Burr Smith, 1975 and 1980.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the research notes, correspondence, and personal papers of Helen Burr Smith, an authority on Colonial American silversmiths and portrait painters.
The collection includes both typed and handwritten notes and drafts, as well as correspondence related to researching, writing and publishing articles on topics of her expertise. Smith was a frequent contributor to the New-York Historical Society Quarterly, the New York Genealogical and Biographical Society Record, American Collector, Antiques Magazine, and the New York Sun newspaper.
Also included are 73 photostats and 1 original document related to colonial American silver and silversmiths. These documents include bills, receipts, and legal writs related to the affairs of the silversmiths themselves, as well as inventories of estates of people who owned objects made of silver.
Smith's personal papers include personal correspondence, family scrapbooks and photo albums, and genealogical research. Correspondence between Smith and her lawyers covers topics such as her rent-controlled apartment in Manhattan, medical bills, and income tax. There are also a few copies of a memoir Smith wrote in 1978, which consists of a series of vignettes about various unrelated incidents in her life. There are also books and journals from Smith's personal library, the most significant of which are her books on silver and silversmiths.
Related Materials
The library holds Smith's two volume Early American Silversmithing. The volumes contain a series of articles written by Smith based on her original research on colonial silversmiths. The articles were published in the New York Sun and Antiques Magazine between 1938-1945. The volumes were apparently assembled by Smith to give to friends. The articles are mimeographed or otherwise copied from clippings of their newspaper and magazine appearances.
Early American Silversmithing, by Helen Burr Smith
Arts and history.; Genealogy.; Goldsmiths.; Material culture.; Silversmiths.; Silverwork, Colonial.; Women historians -- United States.; Personal papers.; Research notes.; Portrait painters.
- Series I: Research, 1939-1978
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of typed and handwritten research notes, drafts, and outlines of articles written by Smith, primarily about early American silversmiths and portraitists. The series is arranged by subject, following Smith's own classification scheme.
  - Silversmiths A-C, 1939-1945 (Offsite-box 77, Box 1)
  - Silversmiths D-G, 1943-1972 (Offsite-box 77, Box 2)
  - Silversmiths H-L, 1943-1965 (Offsite-box 77, Box 3)
  - Silversmiths M-R, 1943-1975 (Offsite-box 78, Box 4)
  - Silversmiths S-W, 1939-1971 (Offsite-box 78, Box 5)
  - Cornwallis' Knee Buckles story, 1940-1958 (Offsite-box 78, Box 6)
  - DePeyster, 1950-1968 (Offsite-box 79, Box 7)
  - Stephen Foster, songwriter, 1938-1950 (Offsite-box 79, Box 8)
  - Ryer Gerritse (R.G.) Tankard, 1944-1978 (Offsite-box 79, Box 9)
  - Michael Hillegas, First Treasurer, 1945-1978 (Offsite-box 80, Box 10)
  - John Mare portrait (1 of 5), 1939-1978 (Offsite-box 80, Box 11)
  - John Mare portrait (2 of 5), 1939-1978 (Offsite-box 80, Box 12)
  - John Mare portrait (3 of 5), 1939-1978 (Offsite-box 81, Box 13)
  - John Mare portrait (4 of 5), 1939-1978 (Offsite-box 81, Box 14)
  - John Mare portrait (5 of 5), 1939-1978 (Offsite-box 15)
  - Jeremiah Platt, 1955-1974 (Offsite-box 81, Box 16)
  - Nicholas Roosevelt, goldsmith, 1941-1978 (Offsite-box 82, Box 17)
  - The Twins, 1967-1969 (Offsite-box 82, Box 18)
    Notes on two sets of identical twin brothers who worked in the antiques business in New Hampshire: Robert and Richard Wiggins, and Reginald and Ronald Bacon.
  - Hendrick Vanderheul, 1947-1971 (Offsite-box 82, Box 19)
  - Silver and Silversmiths, miscellaneous items, 1939-1978 (Offsite-box 83, Box 20)
  - Special Notes and correspondence for articles, seminars, and projects (1 of 7), 1939-1978 (Offsite-box 83, Box 21)
  - Special Notes and correspondence for articles, seminars, and projects (2 of 7), 1939-1978 (Offsite-box 83, Box 22)
  - Special Notes and correspondence for articles, seminars, and projects (3 of 7), 1939-1978 (Offsite-box 84, Box 23)
  - Special Notes and correspondence for articles, seminars, and projects (4 of 7), 1939-1978 (Offsite-box 84, Box 24)
  - Special Notes and correspondence for articles, seminars, and projects (5 of 7), 1939-1978 (Offsite-box 84, Box 25)
  - Special Notes and correspondence for articles, seminars, and projects (6 of 7), 1939-1978 (Offsite-box 85, Box 26)
  - Special Notes and correspondence for articles, seminars, and projects (7 of 7), 1939-1978 (Offsite-box 98, Box 27)
- Series II: General Correspondence, 1938-1979
  This series includes research and reference correspondence with academics, librarians and other sources. The "Special Letters" are those letters Smith designated as such, presumably for their praise of her work.
  - Correspondence A, 1938-1976 (Offsite-box 85, Box 28)
  - Correspondence B, 1939-1979 (Offsite-box 85, Box 29)
  - Correspondence C, 1939-1978 (Offsite-box 86, Box 30)
  - Correspondence D, 1942-1946 (Offsite-box 86, Box 31)
  - Correspondence E-G, 1949-1970 (Offsite-box 86, Box 32)
  - Correspondence H, 1944-1977 (Offsite-box 87, Box 33)
  - Correspondence I, 1940-1945 (Offsite-box 87, Box 34)
  - Correspondence K-L, 1946-1970 (Offsite-box 87, Box 35)
  - Correspondence M-N, 1939-1966 (Offsite-box 88, Box 36)
  - Correspondence O-P, 1942-1978 (Offsite-box 88, Box 37)
  - Correspondence R (1 of 2), 1938-1970 (Offsite-box 88, Box 38)
  - Correspondence R (2 of 2), 1938-1970 (Offsite-box 89, Box 39)
  - Correspondence S, 1938-1971 (Offsite-box 89, Box 40)
  - Correspondence T-V, 1949-1974 (Offsite-box 89, Box 41)
  - Correspondence W, 1938-1971 (Offsite-box 90, Box 42)
  - Correspondence W-Z, 1939-1966 (Offsite-box 90, Box 43)
  - Correspondence Special Letters, 1938-1952 (Offsite-box 90, Box 44)
- Series III: Catalogs, 1938-1975
  This series mainly consists of museum and auction catalogs with a focus on silver items and early American art. There are a few pamphlets on church and local histories as well.
  - Catalogs - Silver (1 of 3), 1940-1970 (Offsite-box 91, Box 45)
  - Catalogs - Silver (2 of 3), 1940-1970 (Offsite-box 91, Box 46)
  - Catalogs - Silver (3 of 3), 1940-1970 (Offsite-box 91, Box 47)
  - Catalogs and Pamphlets - paintings and miscellaneous (1 of 4), 1938-1975 (Offsite-box 92, Box 48)
  - Catalogs and Pamphlets - paintings and miscellaneous (2 of 4), 1938-1975 (Offsite-box 92, Box 49)
  - Catalogs and Pamphlets - paintings and miscellaneous (3 of 4), 1938-1975 (Offsite-box 92, Box 50)
  - Catalogs and Pamphlets - paintings and miscellaneous (4 of 4), 1938-1975 (Offsite-box 93, Box 51)
- Series IV: Documents Relating to Colonial Silver, undated
  This series consists of 73 photostats and 1 original document, mostly concerning colonial American silver and silversmiths. Some items, such as bills, receipts, and legal writs, relate to the affairs of the silversmiths themselves. Other items are inventories of estates and households of people who owned objects made of silver.
  - Original Document, undated (Offsite-box 97, Box 52)
    One small handwritten inventory, unidentified. Smith's notes indicate "I have no idea whose estate it is from."
  - Copies of Documents, undated (Offsite-box 97, Box 52)
    Includes 73 photostats of documents mainly concerning colonial American silversmiths such as: Paul Revere, Joseph Anthony, Jr., Curry & Preston, Griffin & Adams, John Mc Allister & Son and others. Some of the documents are accounts, receipts, bills and other papers relating to the affairs of the silversmiths themselves. Other are household and estate inventories listing the property of Thomas & Sarah Richie of Philadelphia, David Verplanck, Margaret & Philip Schuyler and others. Of special interest is a 28-page photostat of the 1749 inventory and accounts of the estate of Adolph Phillipse of Phillipse Manor, N.Y.
- Series V: Personal Papers, 1918-1980
  This series consists of personal correspondence, family scrapbooks and photo albums, and genealogical research. It also includes correspondence between Smith and her lawyers about various matters, including her rent-controlled apartment in Manhattan, medical bills, and income tax. There are also a few copies of a memoir Smith wrote in 1978, which consists of a series of vignettes about various unrelated incidents in her life.
  - Family Portrait Albums (1 of 2), undated (Offsite-box 97, Box 53)
  - Family Portrait Albums (2 of 2), undated (Offsite-box 99, Box 54)
  - Family History Records and Papers (1 of 3), 1919-1978 (Offsite-box 98, Box 55)
  - Family History Records and Papers (2 of 3), 1919-1978 (Offsite-box 93, Box 56)
  - Family History Records and Papers (3 of 3), 1919-1978 (Offsite-box 93, Box 57)
  - Family History Scrapbooks, 1918-1978 (Offsite-box 99, Box 58)
  - Income Tax, 1961-1965 (Offsite-box 94, Box 59)
  - Rent Control, 1954-1978 (Offsite-box 94, Box 60)
  - Lawyers - Robert McCullough and Martin Block, 1931-1978 (Offsite-box 94, Box 61)
  - Lawyers - Vincent West, 1948-1974 (Offsite-box 95, Box 62)
  - Medical - Blue Cross Blue Shield, 1964-1976 (Offsite-box 95, Box 63)
  - Medical - General, 1970-1979 (Offsite-box 95, Box 64)
  - Memoir copies and personal items, 1970-1980 (Offsite-box 65)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1938-1978 (Offsite-box 96, Box 66)
  - Personal Correspondence A-M, 1932-1977 (Offsite-box 96, Box 67)
  - Personal Correspondence M-Z, 1932-1979 (Offsite-box 96, Box 68)
- Series VI: Published Volumes, 1920-1970
  This series consists of books and journals from Smith's personal library, the most significant of which are her books on silver and silversmiths. The publications are arranged by subject.
  - Silver and Silversmiths (1 of 2), 1927-1970 (Offsite-box 69)
    Titles include:
    Early American Silversmiths Vol.II by Helen Burr Smith, 1945.
    English Silver 1675-1825 by Stephen G.C. Ensko and Edward Wenham, 1937.
    Quebec and Montreal Silversmiths by Marius Barbeau, 1940.
    Early New York Silver by C. Louise Avery, 1931.
    American Silver by Kathryn C. Buhler, 1950.
    The Old Silver of Quebec by Ramsay Traquair, 1940.
    The Philip Leffingwell Spalding Collection of Early American Silver by Edwin J. Hipkiss, 1943.
    American Silversmiths and Their Marks, Volumes I and II, by Stephen G.C. Ensko, 1927 and 1937.
    Indian Ornaments Made by Philadelphia Silversmiths by Harold E. Gillingham, 1936.
    South Carolina Silversmiths 1690-1860 by E. Milby Burton, 1942.
    Silverware, U.S. Tariff Commission Report, 1940.
    Anglican Church Plate by James Gilchrist, 1967.
    American Silver by John Marshall Phillips, 1949.
    English Goldsmiths and Their Marks by Sir Charles J. Jackson, 1921.
    The Antiques Book by Alice Winchester, 1950.
    American Silver in the Yale University Art Gallery by Kathryn C. Buhler and Graham Hood, 1970.
  - Silver and Silversmiths (2 of 2), 1927-1970 (Offsite-box 70)
  - Biography and biographical reference, 1920-1960 (Offsite-box 71)
  - Children's books and fiction (1 of 2), 1920-1950 (Offsite-box 72)
  - Children's books and fiction (2 of 2), 1920-1950 (Offsite-box 73)
  - Genealogy, 1920-1965 (Offsite-box 74)
  - Journals, 1938-1970 (Offsite-box 73)
    Consists mainly of publications in which Helen Burr Smith's articles appear, including the New-York Historical Society Quarterly.
  - Local history - New York State and New Hampshire, 1920-1960 (Offsite-box 75)
  - Local history - Pennsylvania and New Jersey, 1930-1965 (Offsite-box 76)